Phillip: Organisations have employment policies
and procedures that exist to help team leaders
and managers, and, in this video, we are going
to be looking at how these can help guide a
manager in dealing with disciplinary issues.
Maddy: Although it can often be best
if appropriate, to address disciplinary
issues informally at first, more serious
issues need to be addressed formally and
organisations should have clearly defined
policies and procedures for this in place,
to make sure everyone is treated fairly.
Organisations that don’t follow
policies and procedures put themselves
at risk of breaking the law.
Phillip: There are two categories of problem
that disciplinary procedures are designed
to respond to Misconduct and Capability.
Misconduct occurs when someone
is behaving inappropriately or
against the organisation’s values
Maddy: Capability issues are to do with
not working to the standard that the
organisation expects from its employees
So, what should a disciplinary procedure include?
• Phillip: A meeting with the employee to tell
them that the disciplinary procedure is underway
• Maddy: An investigation to
find out what’s going on
• Phillip: An option to suspend
the person involved, if necessary
• Maddy: A formal disciplinary hearing, which
will be a meeting of everyone involved
• Phillip: If necessary, a sanction against
the person, which can include being dismissed
• Maddy: An option to appeal the
decision and an appeal meeting
• Phillip: Final confirmation of
the decision that’s been made
Maddy: And, throughout this process, the person
in question has the right to be accompanied
by a colleague or a union representative.
Phillip: This is the minimum disciplinary
policy an employer should have, but what other
policies can an employer have, that can help a
team leader or manager with disciplinary issues?
Maddy: Timekeeping
Having a formal policy around timekeeping can
be useful to prevent absenteeism, when employees
take time off without permission or a good reason.
Typically, a timekeeping policy would mean
that most employees are required to accurately
log the time they arrive and leave work.
They may also have to log the time that they
spend on individual projects or pieces of work.
This can make it easier to spot
absenteeism and makes it less likely
that people will be absent without leave.
Phillip: Conduct Policy
This formally describes the conduct that
an employer expects from its employees.
Typically, it will state that employees
are expected to follow the organisation’s
values, treat each other respectfully,
and not bully, harass, or discriminate.
It may also have rules specific to the
organisation, like defining how equipment
should be treated, and attitudes expected
when dealing with external clients, and so on.
Maddy: This helps show what behaviour is
acceptable or unacceptable and is also a useful
reference for a team leader as to when and if it’s
necessary to take disciplinary actions or not.
Phillip: Gross misconduct
There are some actions, like theft or
physical violence, where an employee can
be dismissed immediately, however, these
still need to be investigated properly
giving an employee chance to respond.
This allows for a quick response to
very serious disciplinary issues.
Maddy: Capability policy
This defines the standard of work that an
organisation expects from its employees
and gives a framework for responding
to the problem of underperforming.
These policies should be focused on identifying
capability issues and giving the employee
opportunities to develop and improve.
They should also support the employee
so their performance can be improved and
provide them with training where necessary.
Phillip: By having policies like this
to refer to and in place, you should be
in a better position as a team leader
to respond to various disciplinary
issues before they become too serious.